# Davide Carminati, Ph.D.

davide.carminati@outlook.com

(+39) 366 434 6599

in davide-carminati

DavideCarminati

Self-motivated, independent researcher in the field of robotics and Bayesian methods and algorithms. His research is focused on real-time stochastic models specifically designed to work on mobile robots for environment modelling by means of depth sensors and system identification. He has experience in control design and embedded system programming. Currently exploring parallel implementation of Bayesian methods for real-time robotic applications involving environment modelling and state estimation. He supervised thesis projects and activities for several Master's students. Interested in pursuing research in robotics.

# Work Experience

11/2024 present

### Industrial Researcher (R&D) – MAVTech s.r.l. (Bolzano, IT)

- Introduced software development into MAVTech Research and Development team.
- Enhanced autonomy and safety during flights through Machine Learning algorithms.

02/2023 -08/2024

# Research Fellow - Politecnico di Torino (IT)

STREAM robotics group – Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering.

- Maintained the robotic platforms in the laboratory for Ph.D. and Master's students.
- Implemented Bayesian algorithms (SMC/Particle Filter, Parallel Tempering) in CUDA for a faster parallel execution.
- Research focused on Bayesian methods for data efficient state-space modelling and estimation for mobile robots.

07/2021 -12/2021

## ■ Intern – IDIAP Research Institute (Martigny, CH)

Robot Learning and Interaction Group – supervisor: Dr. Sylvain Calinon.

- Dealt with probabilistic methods applied to robots.
- Dived into probabilistic modeling of environments and ergodic trajectory planners.

02/2020 -08/2024

#### Collaborator – Politecnico di Torino (IT)

- 2<sup>nd</sup> level Master in Space Exploration and Development Systems: Gave lectures on Guidance, Navigation and Control (GNC) algorithms, and hardware and software technologies for aerospace.
- Flight Simulation, Master of Science in Aerospace Engineering: Introduced students to C++/Python programming in ROS under a Linux environment.

### **Education**

11/2019 -11/2023

# Ph.D. in Aerospace Engineering – Politecnico di Torino (IT)

Thesis title: Bayesian-based algorithms for Modeling and Identification for Autonomous Robotic Systems.

- Applied Gaussian process regression to ground robots for a data-efficient modelling of their surroundings using depth sensors, as well as for identifying their dynamics.
- Developed and tested Gaussian process-based algorithms onto customized ground robotic platforms with limited computational resources for real-time applications.

2017 - 2019

#### M.Sc., Mechatronic Engineering – Politecnico di Torino (IT)

Thesis title: Design and Testing of Indoor UAS Control Techniques. GPA: 110/110

# **Education (continued)**

## **Skills**

Coding

Regular user of C++ and MATLAB/Simulink. Good command of Python and CUDA. Experience with microcontroller programming and real-time operating systems (ARM Mbed OS). Basic knowledge of Bash and Julia.

Operating Systems

Ubuntu, Windows, ARM MbedOS for embedded platforms.

Libraries

Robot Operating System (ROS), Point Cloud Library (PCL), Eigen3, cuBLAS, cuSOLVER, OpenCV, TensorFlow 2.x/Keras.

CAD and 3D printing

Good command of Autodesk Inventor, Solidworks and Simplify3D.

Languages

Italian (Native), English (Fluent), Spanish (Fluent).

Misc.

Git, LATEX typesetting and publishing, Docker.

### **Research Publications**

- D. Carminati, "Parallel Gaussian process with kernel approximation in CUDA," 2024, (pre-print submitted to journal). @URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12797.
- I. D. D. M. De Pierrepont Franzetti, R. Parin, D. Carminati, and E. Capello, "Modelling of ground and ceiling effects for quadcopters based on experimental data," in 2024 International Conference on Unmanned Aircraft Systems (ICUAS), 2024, pp. 405–412. ODOI: 10.1109/ICUAS60882.2024. 10557056.
- 3 D. Carminati, Bayesian-based algorithms for Modeling and Identification for Autonomous Robotic Systems. Politecnico di Torino, 2023, Doctoral thesis.
- M. Mancini, E. I. Trombetta, D. Carminati, and E. Capello, "Adaptive sliding mode control with artificial potential field for ground robots in precision agriculture," in 2023 IEEE International Workshop on Metrology for Agriculture and Forestry (MetroAgriFor), 2023, pp. 325–330. © DOI: 10.1109/MetroAgriFor58484.2023.10424132.
- E. I. Trombetta, D. Carminati, and E. Capello, "Nonlinear UGV Identification Methods via the Gaussian Process Regression Model for Control System Design," *Applied Sciences*, vol. 12, no. 22, p. 11769, 2022.
- 6 E. I. Trombetta, I. D. D. M. de Pierrepont, D. Carminati, M. Scanavino, and E. Capello, "Data-Driven Identification Method and Simulation Modeling of a Ground Robot," en, in 2021 IEEE International Workshop on Metrology for AeroSpace, 2021, p. 6.
- I. D. D. M. de Pierrepont, D. Carminati, M. Scanavino, E. Capello, et al., "Model-In-the-Loop Testing of Control Systems and Path Planner Algorithms for QuadRotor UAVs," in 2020 International Conference on Unmanned Aircraft Systems (ICUAS), IEEE, 2020, pp. 1809–1818.

# References

#### Prof. Elisa Capello

Full Professor

Politecnico di Torino,

Corso Duca degli Abruzzi 24, 10129, Turin, Italy.

≥ elisa.capello@polito.it